Guide to the Loudoun-Cumberland Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Loudoun-Cumberland collection
1748-1763
MS 332
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
3
The colletion is composed of papers relating to the British presence in North America during the French and Indian War and consists of correspondence and reports describing military actions, royal decrees, lists of supplies and armaments, and other items of a similar nature. The first part of the collection contains typewritten transcripts of the papers of William Augustus, Duke of Cumberland (1721-1765), copied from originals in the Royal Library at Windsor Castle. The second part consists of photostatic copies of the papers of John Campbell, 4th earl of Loudoun, (1705-1782).
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Stanley Pargellis, 1942
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The Loudon-Cumberland Collection is composed of papers relating to the British presence in North America during the French and Indian War. Included is correspondence and reports describing military actions, royal decrees, lists of supplies and so forth.
Two groups of papers make up the collection. The first contains type-written transcripts of the papers of William Augustus, Duke of Cumberland (1721-1765), captain general of the British army from 1745 to 1757. They are copied from originals in the Royal Library at Windsor Castle. The second part consists of photostatic copies of the papers of John Campbell, fourth Earl of Loudon (1705-1782), the commander-in-chief of British forces in America from 1756-1758. These are taaken from originals in the Huntington Library and should not be reproduced without the permission of the Huntington Library.
Oversize material from each set has been placed in a folio. Cross-references to this material have been inserted in the folders at the proper chronological places.
Both sets of papers were the gift of Stanley Pargellis, professor of history at Yale University, in 1942.
Seven Years' War, 1756-1763; Europe; United States -- History -- French and Indian War, 1754-1763; William Augustus, Prince, Duke of Cumberland, 1721-1765; Loudoun, John Campbell, Earl of, 1705-1782
- Inventory, 1748-1763, n.d.
  - Papers of William Augustus, Duke of Cumberland (transcripts)
    - 1748 - 1754 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - 1755 January - October (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - 1755 November - 1756 May (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - 1756 June - July (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - 1756 August (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - 1756 September - December (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - 1757 January - April (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - 1757 May - June (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - 1757 July (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - 1757 August (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - 1757 September -1763, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Papers of John Campbell, 4th Earl of Loudon (photostatic copies)
    - 1755 - 1756 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - 1757 - 1758 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - n.d. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Oversize (Box 2)